<glossary>
	<title>Glossary</title>
	<para>
		This is the glossary for the Wolframe Application Building Manual. Although it
		covers most of the terms used in the Wolframe world, some terms might be skipped
		if they are rarely used in this context. These terms are explained in the
		Application Building Manual.
	</para>


<glossdiv><title>External glossary</title>

	<glossentry id="DDL"><glossterm>Data Definition Language</glossterm>
		<acronym>DDL</acronym>
		<glossdef>
			<para>A domain specific language for describing data structures</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>Wolframe glossary</title>

	<glossentry><glossterm>Connection Handler</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Interface for the networking to one client/server connection during its whole lifetime.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	<glossentry><glossterm>Command Handler</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Interface for delegating processing of client protocol commands in a hierarchical way. A command handler is created by a connection handler or another command handler. During command execution the input/output of the connection is entirely handled by the command handler. Command Handlers are used to build the communication protocol processing as hierarchical state machine.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	<glossentry><glossterm>Program</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>A set of named units of description of processing or data in a source file. The source file is loaded at server startup.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	<glossentry><glossterm>Transaction</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>A transaction is a call of a database defined in a transaction program. A transaction either fails completely or succeeds as whole. Auditing is seen as part of the transaction. Transactions have an object as input and return an object or an error as result.
				Authorization tags that are checked against the user privileges of the connection can be attached to transactions.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	<glossentry><glossterm>Lua</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Lua (www.lua.org) is a scripting language. It is used in Wolframe as one language for writing programs. It distinguishes itself by being lightweight. It has to be lightweight because the language context has to be recreated with every start of a clients command execution for security reasons.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	<glossentry><glossterm>Filter</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Filters are attached to network input and output to read and write input in a well defined format. Filters let you process input and print output in an iterative way. Filters are loaded by the system at startup and have a unique name.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	<glossentry><glossterm>Form</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>A form is a hierarchical description of typed data. Forms are used to create objects from a serialization and to validate input. Forms are defined in programs written in a DDL (Data Definition Language) or as declared as part of a build-in function API.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry><glossterm>Channel</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>The flow for a single connection. Not all objects have channels (e.g. databases).
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	<glossentry><glossterm>Group</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>A set of objects of the same type seen as one single object for the objects that use it.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	<glossentry><glossterm>Unit</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>An element of a group. A group is a set of units.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	<glossentry><glossterm>Provider</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>An entity providing objects of a kind. Some providers are factories, but not all of them.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	<glossentry id="EoD"><glossterm>End Of Data (EoD)</glossterm>
		<abbrev>EoD</abbrev>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Marks the end of a complete data unit to be processed by a processor. 
			End of data is marked with CR LF dot ('.') CR LF or LF dot LF. For passing 
			lines with a dot ('.') at the start of a content line, the client has to 
			escape an LF dot in the content with LF dot dot. This escaping applies 
			also to the result returned to the client. 
			So client has to unescape LF dot sequences by replacing them by a LF.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	<glossentry><glossterm>Application Reference Path</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>The application server defines this file path where all relative paths defined in the configuration refer to.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>A</title>

	<glossentry id="AAAA"><glossterm><acronym>AAAA</acronym></glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Acronym for Authentication, Authorization, Accounting and Auditing</para>
			<glossseealso otherterm="Authentication">Authentication</glossseealso>
			<glossseealso otherterm="Authorization">Authorization</glossseealso>
			<glossseealso otherterm="Accounting">Accounting</glossseealso>
			<glossseealso otherterm="Auditing">Auditing</glossseealso>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="Authentication"><glossterm>Authentication</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Authentication is a process that creates a login for the user,
			granting him access to parts of the system.</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="Authorization"><glossterm>Authorization</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Authorization grant or deny the execution of functions or
			database transactions based on rules on the client login of the session
			(Authentication).
			You can specify such access rules on different levels of processing.</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="Accounting"><glossterm>Accounting</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para></para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="Auditing"><glossterm>Auditing</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Auditing describes a special kind of logging of transactions.
			Audit operations are represented as function calls.
			Audit operations specified as critical are handled as a critical part 
			of the transaction. If a critical audit operation fails then the 
			transaction fails (rollback).</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>S</title>
	<glossentry id="SSL"><glossterm><acronym>SSL</acronym></glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Secure Sockets Layer</para>
			<para>Cryptographic protocols which provide secure communications on the Internet.
			SSL is a predecessor to TLS</para>
			<glossseealso otherterm="TLS">TLS</glossseealso>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>T</title>
	<glossentry id="TLS"><glossterm><acronym>TLS</acronym></glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Transport Layer Security</para>
			<para>Transport Layer Security (TLS) and its predecessor, Secure Sockets Layer (SSL),
			are cryptographic protocols that provide communication security over the Internet.
			TLS and SSL encrypt the segments of network connections above the Transport Layer,
			using asymmetric cryptography for key exchange, symmetric encryption for privacy,
			and message authentication codes for message integrity.</para>
			<glossseealso otherterm="SSL">SSL</glossseealso>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

</glossary>
