<sect2>
	<title>Define Custom Data Types</title>
	<para>In this chapter we introduce how to declare a custom data type in a module.
	Custom data types can be used in scripting language bindings and as normalizers
	referenced in a <code>.wnmp</code> file (type normalization declaration file, see section 
	"Data Types in DDLs" in the chapter "Forms" of the "Application Development Manual")
	First we introduce the data structures you
	have to know to implement a custom data type and then we will show the module building
	block to declare a custom data type in a module.
	</para>

	<sect3>
	<title>Custom Data Type Interface</title>
	<para>
	A custom data type definition involves 3 classes: CustomDataType,CustomDataValue and CustomDataInitializer.
	The CustomDataInitializer class is optional and only needed when value construction has to
	be parametrized. If an initializer is involved then it is created and passed as argument to
	the method constructing the custom data type value (class CustomDataValue).
	The class CustomDataType defines the custom data type and all its methods defined.
	The class CustomDataValue defines a value instance of this type.
	The class CustomDataInitializer, if specified, defines an object describing the parametrization
	of the value construction. An example of an initializer could be the format of a date or
	the precision in a fixed point number. The following listings show these interfaces:
	</para>
	<sect4>
	<title>CustomDataType Structure</title>
	<para>The class to build the custom data type definition structure composed of methods added 
	with <code>CustomDataType::define( .. )</code>. From this class we do not derive. We incrementally
	add method by method by calling <code>CustomDataType::define( .. )</code> in the type constructor
	function.
	</para>
	<programlisting language='C++'>
<xi:include  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/ExtDevelopment/customDataType.hpp" parse="text" />
	</programlisting>
	</sect4>

	<sect4>
	<title>CustomDataInitializer Interface</title>
	<para>The custom data inizializer definition. From this class we have to derive our own
	initializer definions.</para>
	<programlisting language='C++'>
<xi:include  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/ExtDevelopment/customDataInitializer.hpp" parse="text" />
	</programlisting>
	</sect4>

	<sect4>
	<title>Class CustomDataValue</title>
	<para>The custom data type value instance definition. From this class we have to derive our own
	custom value definions.
	</para>
	<programlisting language='C++'>
<xi:include  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/ExtDevelopment/customDataValue.hpp" parse="text" />
	</programlisting>
	</sect4>
	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	<title>Building Blocks</title>
	<para>
	When you include "appdevel/customDatatypeModuleMacros.hpp" or simply "appDevel.hpp" you get 
	the building block declared to build a custom data type in a module. 
	</para>

	<sect4>
	<title>Declaring a custom data type</title>
	<para>The following declaration shows a declaration of a simple custom data type.
	</para>
	<programlisting language='C++'>
    WF_CUSTOM_DATATYPE(name,constructor)
	</programlisting>
	<para>where name is the identifier string of the function in the system and constructor a
	function with the following signature:

	<programlisting language='C++'>
<xi:include  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="examples/ExtDevelopment/customDataTypeConstructor.hpp" parse="text" />
	</programlisting>
	</para>
	</sect4>
	</sect3>
</sect2>

