<sect1>
	<title>Eliminating Interface Defects</title>
	<para>
		Functional defects in the user interface like for example syntax errors in the
		definitions of the request answer can be eliminated by inspecting the error messages
		reported by the <application>wolfclient</application> in developer mode
		and fixing the interface accordingly.
	</para>
	<sect2>
		<title>Switch the Developer Mode On</title>

		<para>In order to inspect the internals of your client program, we have first
		to switch on "Developer Mode" in the "Developer" context of the "Preferences Dialog".
		The following picture emphasizes the check box you have to enable (highlighted green).
		</para>
		<screenshot>
			<screeninfo>Enable Debug Window</screeninfo>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata fileref="images/clients/preferences_developper_develmode.png" format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata fileref="images/clients/preferences_developper_develmode.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</screenshot>

	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>Inspect Errors and Warnings and Debug Messages Reported</title>

		<para>To inspect internal messages reported by the <application>wolfclient</application>
		in developer mode we have to open the debug window.
		The debug window is opened by clicking on the bug icon in the
		main tool bar or via the developer context menu. The following picture
		shows an example debug output. Each action we do from now on with
		the debug window opened can be followed on the level of messages it emits.
		</para>
		<para>
		We can see the messages in the message list when clicking on the
		"Refresh" button. The navigation allows us to restrict our focus 
		on messages on a node in the object tree by clicking on it. 
		Clicking on the root node shows all messages in the recent history.
		The history starts with the last main node created
		before opening the debug window. All message restrictions
		show the messages in order of their emission. We can restrict also on
		the severity of messages in the severity level selection (the select
		box set to "Debug" as default left of the "Refresh" button).
		</para>
		<para>
		The "Clear" button allows us to empty the recent history without closing
		the debug window.
		</para>
		<screenshot>
			<screeninfo>Debug Window</screeninfo>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata fileref="images/clients/debug_window.png" format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata fileref="images/clients/debug_window.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</screenshot>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
