<glossary>
	<title>Glossary</title>
	<para>
		This is the glossary for the Wolframe Service Development Kit. Although it
		covers most of the terms used in the Wolframe world, some terms might be skipped
		if they are rarely used in the SDK context. These terms are explained in the
		Application Building Manual
	</para>

<glossdiv><title>E</title>

	<glossentry id="xml"><glossterm>Extensible Markup Language</glossterm>
		<acronym>XML</acronym>
		<abbrev>ISO 8879:1986</abbrev>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Some reasonable definition here. BTW, this just an example.</para>
			<glossseealso otherterm="xml">loop to XML</glossseealso>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>Our glossary</title>

	<glossentry><glossterm>Application Processor</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>The module that executes the scripts of the user application called by the
				connection handler. An application processor is assigned to exactly one connection
				handler during its lifetime.</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry><glossterm>Application Processor Program</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Program or script executed by the application processor.
				The program or script works with input, output and system calls
				as only interface to the system. System exceptions, signals and events
				are handled in the background through yield execution.</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry><glossterm>Connection Handler</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Interface for the networking to one client/server connection during its whole lifetime.</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry><glossterm>Closure</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<glossseealso><ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Closure_%28computer_science%29">wikipedia</ulink></glossseealso>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="EoD" ><glossterm>End Of Data</glossterm>
		<abbrev>EoD</abbrev>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Marks the end of the content to be processed by the application processor.
				End of data is marked with CR LF '.' CR LF or LF '.' LF.
				For passing lines with a dot '.' at the start of a content line,
				the client has to escape an LF '.' in the content with LF '.' '.'.</para>
			<glossseealso otherterm="EoM">EoM</glossseealso>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry id="EoM"><glossterm>End Of Message</glossterm>
		<abbrev>EoM</abbrev>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Marks the end of a network input message.
				End of message is handled by the application processor generator function
				without showing up to the application processor program (yield execution).</para>
			<glossseealso otherterm="EoD">EoD</glossseealso>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry><glossterm>Generator</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Generators are defined for the application processor to implement
				iterators on network input or system call results.</para>
			<glossseealso><ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generator_%28computer_science%29">wikipedia</ulink></glossseealso>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry><glossterm>Network Input</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>Data passed from the networking framework to the connection handler for processing.</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry><glossterm>Application Reference Path</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>The application server defines this file path where all relative paths
			defined in the configuration refer to.</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry><glossterm>Yield execution</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>The application processor yields execution and gives control
				back to the connection handler, when it cannot continue execution.
				The connection handler has to resume with an action returned
				to the networking framework, that fetches the resources needed by
				the application processor to continue.</para>
			<glossseealso><ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coroutine">wikipedia yield in coroutine</ulink></glossseealso>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

</glossdiv>
</glossary>
